<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The moderate Christian a sermon preached in Exeter at a trienniall visitation of the Reverend Father in God, Ioseph Lord Bishop of that see. March 24. 1630. By Iohn Bury, sometime Fellow of Baliol Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Bury, John, 1580-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842849</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842849</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17335)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1196:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The moderate Christian a sermon preached in Exeter at a trienniall visitation of the Reverend Father in God, Ioseph Lord Bishop of that see. March 24. 1630. By Iohn Bury, sometime Fellow of Baliol Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Bury, John, 1580-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby, for Nathaniell Butter at Saint Anstins [sic] Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The comma after "Christian" on the title page is turned.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7542:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7542:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MODERATE CHRISTIAN. A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED IN EXETER AT A Triennall Viſitation of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father in God</hi> IOSEPH LORD BISHOP of that See. <hi>March</hi> 24. 1630. BY <hi>John Bury,</hi> ſometime Fellow of <hi>Baliol</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Stansby</hi> for <hi>Nathaniell Butter</hi> at Saint <hi>Anſtins</hi> Gate. 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7542:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7542:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, <hi>Joſeph</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> the fruits of Peace, and Holineſſe be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly multiplied.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY GOOD LORD:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Teddily and happily go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>Arke</hi> of God, when it is drawne by <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Holines</hi> tied together <hi>(Heb. 12.14.)</hi> as thoſe two milch kine <hi>keeping the high way, and turning not aſide</hi> to either hand. <hi>Belial</hi> hateth this <hi>Yoke;</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:7542:3"/>(ſeeing his Image <hi>falleth,</hi> where the Arke <hi>ſtandeth)</hi> ſtriveth either to <hi>kill</hi> or <hi>ſever,</hi> yea, by <hi>ſevering</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> theſe bleſſed yoke-fellowes. He hath a <hi>bridle</hi> for Peace, to draw her backe from Holines, and a <hi>Spurre</hi> for Holines to gallop away from Peace. Needs muſt he therefore maligne your Lordſhip, as his profeſſed enemy, both in your <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>government.</hi> How doth hee fret to ſee in your breſt the <hi>ſacred fire</hi> of Devotion, ſo guarded with a pious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that he cannot reach it either with his <hi>Water,</hi> or his <hi>Gunpowder?</hi> How doth it gnaw him to <hi>heare</hi> your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation charge, ſo vehemently bent with equall ſeveritie againſt his two darlings, <hi>Faction,</hi> and <hi>Prophaneſſe;</hi> &amp; to <hi>ſee</hi> your carefull weeding out the <hi>Tares</hi> of Schiſme, without pulling up any <hi>Corne</hi> of true Piety? With what
<pb facs="tcp:7542:3"/>indignation doth he <hi>feele</hi> for the preſent, and <hi>feare</hi> for the future, the prevalent ſucceſse of your milde <hi>ſun-ſhine,</hi> beyond the force of a bluſtring <hi>wind?</hi> no wonder then, if while you breake his <hi>head,</hi> he bite at your <hi>heele;</hi> traducing both your <hi>holy peaceableneſſe,</hi> as not enemy enough to <hi>Rome,</hi> and your <hi>peaceable holines,</hi> as too much friend to <hi>Factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> But how could Integrity be better <hi>cleared,</hi> then by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus <hi>accuſed?</hi> No fairer testimonie of an <hi>impartiall</hi> arbitrement, then the repining of <hi>both</hi> Parties; and it is the common lot both of <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Veritie,</hi> to be buffeted on both cheekes by the <hi>two extreames.</hi> What pitie it is, that <hi>men</hi> ſhould <hi>put aſunder thoſe whom God hath coupled together?</hi> and caſt ſuch <hi>iealouſies</hi> betweene theſe two Daughters of Ieruſalem, that whoſoever is a <hi>Suiter</hi> to the one, is ſuſpected &amp; cenſured of <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting,</hi> if not <hi>contemning</hi> the other?
<pb facs="tcp:7542:4"/>I was willing to ſtep in (though perhaps with as little thanke) as <hi>Moſes</hi> betweene the two ſtriving Iſraelites: <hi>Sirs, ye are Siſters: why ſhould</hi> iealous distracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſet you at variance?</p>
            <p>But finding my ſelfe too weake, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated S. <hi>Paul</hi> to interpoſe, a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond exception, <hi>deeply</hi> and <hi>equally</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in both parties: who more peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able? <hi>pleaſing all men in all things;</hi> yet who more zealous? <hi>not ſeeking</hi> his <hi>owne profite, but the profite of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp;c.</hi> That it now is preached <hi>on the houſe top,</hi> which lately was ſpoken in <hi>the eare,</hi> is but in proſecution of my text, <hi>ſeeking the profite of many, that they may be ſaved.</hi> The ſucceſse I commend to the God of peace and holineſſe, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom I covet to be and approve my ſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all duty and ſervice to be commanded. IOHN BVRY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7542:4"/>
            <head>THE MODERATE CHRISTIAN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. COR. 10.</hi> ult.</bibl>
                  <p>Even as I pleaſe all men in all things, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe Leviticall Ordinances of the Ceremoniall Law,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in meates and drinkes, &amp;c.</hi> as they were borne <hi>mortall,</hi> in their inſtitution, <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed untill the time of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> ſo they had <hi>given up the ghoſt,</hi> with Chriſts <hi>conſummatum eſt,</hi> but were yet
<note n="b" place="margin">Auſtine.</note> allowed a time to prepare for their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent interring.</hi> Vntill which funerall, wherein the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> people of divers and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepant mettall were to be <hi>caſt</hi> into one body, it was thought fit in the meane time to <hi>ſoder</hi> them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by ſome uniformitie. And to this purpoſe the firſt <hi>Synode</hi> of the Chriſtian Church aſſembled in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> made that Eccleſiaſticall <hi>Constitution</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:7542:5"/>for the time, that the converted <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.29,</note> 
               <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from meates ſacrificed to Idols, and from ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, and from blood:</hi> and ſhortly after <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> going in <hi>viſitation,</hi> exacted the practice of that Canon, and gave out the Booke of <hi>Articles:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.4.</note> 
               <hi>And as they went through the Cities,</hi> they delivered them the Decrees for to keepe, that were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Apoſtles and Elders, &amp;c. Whether the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (as ſome contend) had not in thoſe ſix yeares betweene that Synod and this Epiſtle, heard of that <hi>Decretall Epiſtle</hi> directed
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.23.</note> onely to the Churches of <hi>Syria and Cilicia,</hi> about a thouſand miles from them, or that they punctually ſtood upon their knowledge <hi>(<note n="f" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.11.</note> Through thy knowledge ſhall the weake brother periſh)</hi> once it ſeemes, that ſome under the colour of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> libertie had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken liberty to be <hi>unchriſtian,</hi> and by ſcandalous ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of meates offered to Idols
<note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>ſinned in woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their brethren;</hi> and through their ſides <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle having begun the cure hereof <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. by <hi>tenting</hi> the <hi>griefe,</hi> now takes it in hand againe to apply the <hi>playſter,</hi> not preſſing the Synodicall Conſtitution, but the <hi>ground</hi> of it, the reaſon of <hi>ſcandall:</hi> and for making and keeping peace he <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth</hi> together the Law of <hi>Charitie</hi> with the Law of <hi>Faith.</hi> The Law of Faith layes abroad the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, omnia licent:</hi> the Law of Charitie contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the <hi>uſe, Omnia non expediunt.</hi> Defect in the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> entrencheth upon Chriſtian <hi>libertie,</hi> exceſſe in the <hi>Vſe</hi> breakes out into unchriſtian <hi>licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Charity</hi> therefore is aſſigned to be the <hi>moderatrix</hi> of Chriſtian <hi>libertie;</hi> caſting one eye to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7542:5"/>
               <hi>God, Charitas in Deum, Verſe</hi> 31. <hi>Whether yee eate, &amp;c.</hi> the other to our <hi>brethren, Charitas in proximum, Verſe</hi> 32. <hi>Give no offence, &amp;c.</hi> which precept that it may the better enter, is <hi>headed</hi> with his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. <hi>Even as I, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A faire example whether wee looke to the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> or the <hi>manner,</hi> his <hi>action,</hi> or his <hi>aime.</hi> In the
<list>
                  <item>1. A plauſible practice: <hi>Even as I.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A profitable purpoſe, <hi>Not ſeeking, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to foure Circumſtantiall queſtions,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Quis,</hi> who is the example: <hi>I, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as I</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Quid,</hi> what is the matter: <hi>pleaſe</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Quibus,</hi> whom: <hi>All men</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Quatenus,</hi> Wherein: <hi>in all things.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond anſwereth one maine queſtion, <hi>Quor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum?</hi> to what end this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>?</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Negatively,</hi> an end <hi>free</hi> from baſe <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Not ſeeking mine owne profit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Affirmatively,</hi> an end <hi>full</hi> of Noble <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi> ſeeking the profit of others: amplified by the Quantitie
<list>
                     <item>Of the Subiect, <hi>Multitude,</hi> no ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, but <hi>the profit of many.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of the Obiect, <hi>Magnitude,</hi> no light bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, but the beſt and greateſt, <hi>that they may be ſaved.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quis. I.]</hi> I that have no leſſe <hi>libertie,</hi> no leſſe <hi>authoritie,</hi> no leſſe <hi>knowledge,</hi> both of my libertie and authoritie then the beſt, yet I pleaſe, doe <hi>even as I.</hi> A right and compendious <hi>methode</hi> of teaching as in all arts, ſo in the Schoole of Pietie. Firſt, a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7542:6"/>rule, <hi>Give no offence,</hi> Secondly, an example, <hi>even as I.</hi> So <hi>Chriſt</hi> our head-ſchoolemaſter:
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.48.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> there is the <hi>precept, as your heavenly Father is perfect,</hi> there is the <hi>patterne.</hi> To teach all by precepts is <hi>tedious: Longum iter per praecepta:</hi> to teach altogether by example is <hi>dangerous:</hi> the rule gives <hi>authoritie,</hi> the example addeth <hi>efficacie,</hi> and where the example followeth the <hi>rule,</hi> we may both more <hi>eaſily,</hi> and more <hi>ſafely</hi> follow the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</hi> But of all examples none ſo pregnant and powerfull, as when the <hi>teacher</hi> voucheth himſelfe for example. <hi>Even as I.</hi> Precepts offer to <hi>drive,</hi> Examples to <hi>lead:</hi> the example of others leadeth by the <hi>eare,</hi> our owne leades by the <hi>hand.</hi> That <hi>practicall</hi> oratory, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.9. <hi>To make our ſelves an example to you to follow us,</hi> is the moſt powerfull <hi>Charme</hi> of Rhetorike, leading people by the <hi>eyes,</hi> as <hi>Hercules</hi> did by the <hi>eares. Even as I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Loe heere an <hi>example</hi> to turne us all into exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Parents, Maſters, Miniſters, to our Children, Servants, Pariſhioners: the way to <hi>make</hi> them ſuch as we deſire, is to <hi>be</hi> our ſelves ſuch as wee would make them: their <hi>mindes</hi> looke out more at their <hi>eye,</hi> then at their <hi>eare,</hi> more attentive to what we <hi>doe,</hi> then what we <hi>require.</hi> If we cheriſh any <hi>vice</hi> in our ſelves, they will cheriſh it as a <hi>vertue: Platoes</hi> ſhort necke, and <hi>Aristotles</hi> crup-ſhoulder had their Schollers as a piece of their <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> Well or ill, they learne to doe, <hi>Even as I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we eſpecially (Reverend Brethren) wee are
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.</note> 
               <hi>the light of the World.</hi> Light? the moſt excellent <hi>Obiect</hi> of the moſt excellent <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and that which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7542:6"/>giveth <hi>luſtre</hi> to all the reſt, but withall it inviteth euery eye to bee <hi>looking on.</hi> It ſtands us the more upon to <hi>looke</hi> to our light, that it
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. v.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>ſhine before men, ut non ſolùm audiant bona verba, ſed &amp; videant bona opera.</hi> They expect we ſhould <hi>tranſlate,</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate our good <hi>words</hi> into good <hi>workes,</hi> and with <hi>fiery tongues</hi> in our heads, to make their
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.32.</note> hearts <hi>burne within them,</hi> while we open the Scriptures; to have alſo
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>our lamps burning in our hands</hi> to light them by a pious converſation. Though we bring them heavenly
<note n="n" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>treaſure,</hi> they are poring on the <hi>earthen veſſell;</hi> but if with Gideon
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.16.</note> we carry our <hi>lamp burning in our pitcher,</hi> and can boldy and ſafely ſay to our followers, As yee ſee me doe, doe yee likewiſe; ſound wee our <hi>trumpet,</hi> and breake our <hi>pitcher,</hi> that our light may ſhine: and <hi>the ſword of the Lord and of Gideon</hi> will doe wonders, to put to flight ſins though ſwarming as <hi>graſhoppers</hi> in our Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>What a reverend <hi>awe</hi> ſhall we ſtamp into our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts, if we do both <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note n="p" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15.</note>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> preach <hi>roundly,</hi> and live <hi>ſquarely,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.7.</note> in all things ſhewing our ſelves a patterne of good workes. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts tell us that the <hi>Lion,</hi> the King of beaſts, and terror of his ſubiects, yet ſtands in feare of a <hi>Cocke,</hi> and of <hi>fire.</hi> The divine Story tels mee as much (<hi>Marke</hi> 6.20.) <hi>Herod</hi> was a <hi>Lion</hi> as well as a
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.32,</note> 
               <hi>Foxe,</hi> The
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.2.</note> feare of a King, is as the roaring of a Lion, and yet <hi>hee feared</hi> poore <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</hi> Was it as he was <hi>fire?</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5 35.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn was a burning and ſhining light, burning</hi> in his zealous prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and <hi>ſhining</hi> in his ſtrict living? or was it as he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7542:7"/>was a <hi>Cocke</hi> crowing to awake him out of ſin, and laying hard at him with his <hi>Non Licet, It is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thee to have thy Brothers wife:</hi> for though this Cocke crowing did not prevaile here ſo much as with
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 16.75.</note> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> to draw bitter teares of ſound <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> yet much it did, he was a <hi>parcell-penitent, he did many things.</hi> But yet me thinks it ſhould not be <hi>Iohns preaching</hi> that hee feared, for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 'twas ſweet to heare him as muſicke, <hi>hee heard him gladly.</hi> For what then did that <hi>Lion</hi> ſo feare this <hi>Cocke?</hi> ſurely it was for the <hi>clapping</hi> of his wings, that as he <hi>crowed</hi> to others, hee rouſed up himſelfe in auſtere <hi>devotion;</hi> the <hi>text</hi> ſaith as much: <hi>Herod feared Iohn knowing that he was a iuſt, and a holy man. Herod</hi> feared <hi>Iohn</hi> not ſo much for the <hi>Thundring</hi> of his preaching, as for the <hi>Lightning</hi> of his life: for what <hi>Nazianzen</hi> hath in his Epitaph on great S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Baſil</hi> was due to this great <hi>Iohn:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. His <hi>words</hi> were <hi>thunder,</hi> his <hi>life lightening.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then may we expect to <hi>feele</hi> life in our doctrine, when our people doe <hi>ſee</hi> doctrine in our life: an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar</hi> life able to ſtrike dumbe all gain ſayers, and rippe up the <hi>hearts</hi> of the profane; that
<note n="y" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25.</note> 
               <hi>falling downe on his face hee may worſhip God and report, Eſt Deus in nobis, agitante caleſcimus illo: that God is in us of a truth.</hi> With what a holy reverence did <hi>Conſtantine</hi> embrace <hi>Paphnutius, Theodoſius</hi> ſtoop to his <hi>Ambroſe?</hi> the Emperours <hi>greatnes</hi> honouring the <hi>goodnes</hi> of their ghoſtly Fathers, and entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their iniunctions as <hi>Oracles, Nec vox homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſonat,</hi> as if
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.11.</note> 
               <hi>God had beene come downe in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of men!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:7542:7"/>
            <p>But alas?
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>how is our ſilver become droſſe? our wine is mingled with water:</hi> the price of our <hi>reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is brought downe by our weariſh <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Our eſteeme and value is growne <hi>lower,</hi> becauſe our light is growne <hi>dimmer. Tempora mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur,</hi> I would <hi>(&amp; nos)</hi> did not <hi>follow,</hi> yea, I wiſh it did not <hi>goe before.</hi> But if we cry out <hi>O tempora;</hi> there want not to cry us downe with <hi>O mores,</hi> and to <hi>excuſe</hi> their contemptuous undervaluing of <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> orders, by <hi>accuſing</hi> our <hi>unholy</hi> diſorders; to ſay we are
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>trampled</hi> upon, becauſe <hi>unſavory ſalt,</hi> good for nothing elſe; and ſcorned as baſe Prieſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſonnes of <hi>Levi</hi> are become
<note n="c" place="margin">1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 2.12.17</note> 
               <hi>the ſons of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial</hi> making the people loath the ſervice of God.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—pudet haec opprobria nobis</l>
               <l>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But ſtay <hi>Doeg:</hi> why doth thy malevolent
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.2.</note> 
               <hi>tongue</hi>' cut like a <hi>ſharpe raſor,</hi> ſhaving all by the ground? Grant <hi>Ahimelech</hi> have beene faulty, muſt
<note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.18.</note> 
               <hi>all</hi> the Prieſts be chopt? Why <hi>Haman;</hi> if <hi>Mordecai</hi> be ſtiffe, muſt a
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſter</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>nationall</hi> deſtruction expiate a <hi>perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> offence? if ſome <hi>few Miniſters</hi> (though thoſe <hi>few</hi> be <hi>too many,</hi> and I wiſh diſcipline might make them <hi>nonc</hi>) but if ſome few be debauched, muſt the <hi>whole calling</hi> be diſgraced? muſt the <hi>Apoſtleſhip</hi> downe if there be one <hi>Iudas</hi> among the <hi>twelve,</hi> yea, one among <hi>twenty?</hi> But <hi>ſalus eſt haec noſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us deare Brethren, make Triacle of this poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and with the more caution carry our ſelves
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>blameleſſe, and harmeleſſe, the Sons of God</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in whoſe coat <hi>Momus</hi> may <hi>find</hi> no hole, but what his malice ſhall <hi>make,</hi> that we may <hi>ſhine in the midſt of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7542:8"/>a crooked and perverſe nation, as lights in the world.</hi> Such lights to our people as the <hi>Starre</hi> to the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>going before them till we</hi> bring them home to Chriſt; that calling them after us, as <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.9. <hi>doe the things which ye have heard and ſeene in me;</hi> to all our Chriſtian exhortations, our good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may come in with <hi>Amen, Even as I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you (Beloved Brethren of the Laity) that uſe to <hi>ſee</hi> the light, and not <hi>heare</hi> the voice, here is no leſſon for you, either to <hi>neglect</hi> your Miniſters good <hi>doctrine,</hi> when his <hi>life</hi> is bad: or to <hi>follow</hi> his bad <hi>life,</hi> when his <hi>doctrine</hi> is good. If his life <hi>confute</hi> his doctrine, you may not ſtand of with <hi>Barak?</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>If thou wilt goe with me I will go;</hi> elſe not. <hi>Noahs Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters</hi> may build a good Arke to <hi>ſave</hi> others, though themſelues be <hi>drowned</hi> for not entring: A <hi>ſicke</hi> Phyſitian may make thee <hi>whole;</hi> and the Feri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may row thee <hi>right,</hi> though his face turne the <hi>contrary</hi> way. If for <hi>heeding</hi> your Miniſters evill life, yee ſhould not <hi>heed</hi> his good Doctrine; take <hi>heede</hi> you be not <hi>Donatus</hi> his Diſciples rather then <hi>Chriſt's,</hi> who tutored the auditors even of Scribes and Phariſes
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math</hi> 23.1.</note> to <hi>doe as they ſay,</hi> though <hi>they ſay and doe not.</hi> If on the other ſide, his doctrine <hi>condemne</hi> his life, he teacheth you better, then to do <hi>even as I.</hi> Examples doe well to <hi>ſecond</hi> rules, not to <hi>make</hi> them: yea rather an example <hi>without,</hi> eſpecially <hi>againſt</hi> a rule, is an <hi>unruly</hi> example. <hi>Lot</hi> in his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, <hi>David</hi> in his adultery, and <hi>Peter</hi> in his denyall give us example not to <hi>truſt</hi> examples e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the beſt. He that will draw after every <hi>light,</hi> may hap to be miſled by ſome <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> or delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7542:8"/>by <hi>rotten</hi> though ſhining <hi>wood.</hi> It is the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prerogative of the Lord Paramount, to <hi>take</hi> from none, but <hi>give</hi> to all, both <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>example.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye holy,</hi> the rule his owne, <hi>As I am holy,</hi> himſelfe the example. His only ſonne onely ſhares with him in this royalty,
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.15.</note> 
               <hi>I have given you an example,</hi> and that example may ſtand for a rule, <hi>that yee ſhould doe as I have done to you;</hi> but all <hi>ſubordinate</hi> examples (like <hi>generaſubalterna</hi>) take from their <hi>ſuperior</hi> as they ſend downe to the <hi>inferior;</hi> nor may you ſafely write after their <hi>Copie,</hi> where they recede from the originall <hi>Archetype:</hi> but muſt alwayes <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,</hi> what we find here <hi>expreſt,</hi> the patterne for <hi>imitation, even as I,</hi> to draw after it a faithfull <hi>limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Be yee followers of me, as I am of Chriſt,</hi> in the very next verſe;
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 15.3.</note> for <hi>Chriſt pleaſed not himſelfe,</hi> I doe pleaſe even as Chriſt: do you even as I <hi>pleaſe,</hi> and that is the <hi>Quid,</hi> The ſecond <hi>quaere,</hi> what is the example. <hi>I pleaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That bedroll of perſecutions which he reckoneth up to theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 11. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> will teach us to underſtand it <hi>conatu non eventu,</hi> I <hi>affect</hi> it, though I cannot alwayes <hi>effect</hi> it: Some are ignorant, and <hi>cannot,</hi> ſome froward and <hi>will not,</hi> ſome envious that <hi>cannot, will not</hi> be pleaſed; but I endeauour to pleaſe all that I can, though I cannot all that I would. But what? is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> now clapt on as a <hi>crowne</hi> on his head, which elſe-where hee ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth off as the <hi>viper</hi> from his <hi>hand?</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Doe I ſeeke to pleaſe men? If I ſhould pleaſe men, I ſhould not be the ſervant of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſtinguiſh then. There is a pleaſing <hi>carnally</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7542:9"/>a pleaſing <hi>Chriſtianly;</hi> the firſt he there <hi>deteſteth</hi> as damnable, the ſecond he here <hi>profeſſeth</hi> as laudable and imitable. Carnall pleaſing is <hi>propterſe,</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth in our ſelves, and our owne ends: Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an pleaſing is <hi>propter Deum,</hi> looketh over and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our ſelves to the ſalvation of men and glory of God, <hi>Not ſeeking mine owne profit, but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of many, that they may be ſaved.</hi> How then did he pleaſe, and not pleaſe men? not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>making merchandize of the Word,</hi> either for <hi>favour, profit,</hi> or <hi>credit,</hi> the three golden Balls that men pleaſers uſually run after. Heare his owne proteſtation 1. <hi>Theſs</hi> 2.5. <hi>Not with flattering words,</hi> to curry favour; <hi>nor a cloake of covetouſnes,</hi> for turpe lucrum; <hi>nor of men ſought we glory,</hi> digito notari &amp; dicier, hic eſt: Thus he did not pleaſe men.</p>
            <p>How then did he pleaſe? <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Wee were gentle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, even as a Nurſe cheriſheth her children:</hi> yea more then a <hi>Nurſe,</hi> a <hi>ſervant,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19. <hi>I have made my ſelfe Servant unto all, that I might gaine the more,</hi> not more <hi>money</hi> to my <hi>purſe,</hi> but more <hi>ſoules</hi> to God. Thus to pleaſe men for Gods ſake, is not to pleaſe <hi>Men</hi> but <hi>God;</hi> yea, <hi>Nonian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homoſed Deus placet,</hi> it is not the Apoſtle, but God by the Apoſtle, that doth pleaſe and gaine.</p>
            <p>Pleaſing hee was both in his <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Converſation:</hi> firſt in teaching hee pleaſed, not ſo much in the <hi>matter, ſeeking placentia</hi> (that is
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.14.</note> a badge of ſalſe Prophets) as for the <hi>manner,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truth <hi>placenter; faithfully</hi> yet <hi>wiſely</hi> to become with men; he could handſomely cloſe
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.27.</note> with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa,</hi> that he might get within him, but would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7542:9"/>never have humored his Vncle <hi>Herod,</hi> with his <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodias,</hi> nor <hi>ſow pillowes under</hi> any ſinners <hi>armehole:</hi> no pleaſing <hi>in diſpendium veritatis,</hi> all his pleaſing was in <hi>Compendium Charitatis.</hi> How eaſily may we trace in his Epiſtles that artificiall piece of Oratory to make and keepe <hi>Benevolos auditores,</hi> to hold their <hi>eares</hi> while he teacheth, and their <hi>hearts,</hi> while he turneth them?</p>
            <p>But there are <hi>Impenitent</hi> ſinners; thoſe hee muſt needs diſpleaſe: yet even in <hi>diſpleaſing</hi> he will <hi>pleaſe</hi> what he may. Muſt hee needes <hi>launce</hi> the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume of ſinne? yet even in that he will <hi>pleaſe:</hi> as the Chirurgion in <hi>Seneca</hi> did by the Kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer: who gently <hi>fomenting</hi> her ſore breaſt, with his launcet <hi>hid</hi> under the ſpunge, opened it ere ſhe was aware. <hi>Si ſcîſſet ferrum praeſens repugnâſſet:</hi> The <hi>Patient</hi> would have beene <hi>impatient,</hi> except with the <hi>Lions heart</hi> of reſolution there were ioyned the <hi>Ladies hand</hi> of tender Compaſſion. The <hi>earthly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded Belly-God</hi> ſhall be told his owne roundly, that
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>their end is damnation,</hi> and yet even there he will <hi>pleaſe:</hi> the <hi>teares</hi> of his eyes ſhall teſtifie the <hi>bleeding</hi> of his heart,
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>I tell you weeping: Gutta ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat lapidem,</hi> ſuch <hi>drops</hi> might pierce even a <hi>ſtony</hi> heart. Thus our Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>And now (deare brethren) iudge whether it be <hi>Apoſtolicall,</hi> to gall our hearers with tart <hi>invectives,</hi> to exaſperate them with conceited <hi>nickes,</hi> and to <hi>pleaſe</hi> our ſelues in <hi>diſpleaſing</hi> them. Did you ever know any ſoule converted, any man cured, with ſuch <hi>gall and vineger?</hi> wee ſhall as ſoone catch fiſh with a <hi>naked hooke.</hi> I may not preſume, I know
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7542:10"/>my unworthines to teach teachers (eſpecially ſuch as many of you) It is our Apoſtle to whom now we all goe to ſchoole, and he teacheth us to <hi>pleaſe,</hi> that wee may <hi>profit.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25, 26. <hi>to inſtruct with meekneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> as the way to <hi>recover</hi> ſoules. <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions</hi> like Pils are naturally <hi>diſtaſtfull,</hi> wee had need adminiſter them with the <hi>ſirrupe</hi> of good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>Yee know, the good Mother <hi>Truth</hi> hath a bad daughter dogging her:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>veritas odium:</hi> our Apoſtle either was, or feared to be haunted with her, <hi>I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your enemy, becauſe I tell you the truth?</hi> now muſt our skill be, to get in the Mother, and keepe out the daughter and how may that be? <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15. let naked <hi>veritie</hi> goe no longer <hi>naked,</hi> but be <hi>clothed</hi> with the robes of her ſiſter <hi>Charitie: Speake the truth in Love;</hi> and then it may be <hi>Hatred</hi> that knoweth her Mother but <hi>naked,</hi> may paſſe by and not owne her in that <hi>attire. Suppreſſe wee</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, eagerneſſe, indignation, and ſuch other paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as may <hi>ariſe</hi> from diſpleaſure in the ſpeaker, and are apt to <hi>breed</hi> diſpleaſure in the hearer; and <hi>expreſſe</hi> a loving feare, a wel-wiſhing tenderneſſe, pitty and ſuch other affections, as are both the <hi>Daughters</hi> and <hi>Mothers</hi> of Love. And to follow our Apoſtle, in this holy art of <hi>pleaſing,</hi> let the ſoules wee labour to ſave, <hi>ſee</hi> in our face, <hi>theare</hi> in our tongue, and <hi>fecle</hi> in our heart, that we <hi>grieve</hi> for their ſinne, and <hi>feare</hi> for their danger, and <hi>pitty</hi> them for both; and ſpeaking out of theſe <hi>bowels</hi> of love and compaſſion, I hope, theſe <hi>precious balmes ſhall not breake their head,</hi> but may in time by Gods
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7542:10"/>grace ſupple and mollifie their heart.</p>
            <p>Againe, he <hi>pleaſed</hi> in his <hi>converſation,</hi> carrying himſelfe not onely with plauſible <hi>affabilitie,</hi> and a gentle <hi>placiditie;</hi> but alſo by a pliable <hi>humilitie</hi> condeſcending to all, that he might give offence to none. <hi>Omnis alteritas diſcors</hi> (ſaith <hi>Boetius</hi>) a ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len <hi>differing</hi> occaſioneth <hi>difference,</hi> while <hi>likeneſſe</hi> breedeth <hi>liking.</hi> Heerein therefore hee <hi>complied</hi> with all ſorts, that <hi>indifferent</hi> things might make no <hi>difference,</hi> he would <hi>conforme</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> ſo farre, as <hi>omnialicent</hi> would reach. A skilfull <hi>fiſher</hi> of men, that could fit his ſeverall <hi>baites</hi> according to the ſeverall <hi>ſeaſons,</hi> and divers <hi>kinds</hi> of fiſh; one time he circumciſeth <hi>Timothy,</hi> to pleaſe the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time hee refuſeth to circumciſe <hi>Titus,</hi> to pleaſe the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> See how hee did turne and winde to give content on all hands. <hi>Cap. preced.</hi> 20. <hi>To the Iew I became a Iew, that I might gaine the Iewes;</hi> to them that are under the Law, as under the Law, that I might gaine them that are under the Law, to them that are without Law, as without Law, &amp;c. I became all things to all men, that by all meanes I might ſave ſome.</p>
            <p>What now <hi>Paul?</hi> become a politique <hi>Proteus,</hi> a time ſerving <hi>Diſſembler?</hi> No: that good Father will come into be his <hi>Compurgator, Non ſimulantis aſtu, ſed compatientis affectu:</hi> All this his <hi>turning,</hi> was but to <hi>turne</hi> them unto God, being <hi>covetous</hi> of nothing but men, and <hi>fiſhing</hi> for nothing but <hi>ſoules;</hi> being loath to looſe ſo precious a <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> by ſtanding on a <hi>circumſtance;</hi> or to hazard a <hi>ſoule,</hi> by nice ſticking at a <hi>Ceremony.</hi> Who will not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7542:11"/>commend, then blame the tender <hi>Nurſe</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> (to whom hee compared himſelfe) for playing the childe, that ſhee may ſtill the childe? or who ever counted it a Diminution to <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> greatneſſe, that he <hi>contracted</hi> and drew in himſelfe, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 4.34. that ſo he might apply <hi>his face to the childes face, his hands to the childs hands, &amp;c.</hi> thereby to recover the dead childe to life? In the like <hi>poſture</hi> is our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Paul,</hi> bowing himſelfe to <hi>pleaſe</hi> that he might <hi>ſave,</hi> and in this poſture calleth upon us to <hi>follow</hi> him, and with him to <hi>follow the things that make for peace, and things whereby one may edifie another. Rom.</hi> 14.19.</p>
            <p>What? peace and edification both to bee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed? and both at once? Not two, but one, or two in one; the things that make for <hi>peace,</hi> make alſo for <hi>edification:</hi> no peace, no edification. <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> the King of peace is the only man to <hi>build</hi> Gods houſe: <hi>Diviſion</hi> is fit to build nothing but <hi>Babel,</hi> confuſion. The <hi>Trowell</hi> is for building, not the <hi>ſword:</hi> the ſword in the other hand of <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias</hi> builders,
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.17.</note> is for neceſſary <hi>defence,</hi> not unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>offence,</hi> to keepe off <hi>enemies,</hi> not to foine at their <hi>fellowes.</hi> Our Maſter is the <hi>Prince of peace; Eſay</hi> 9.6. and his flocke are peaceable, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive creatures; not ſnarling <hi>Dogs,</hi> but gentle <hi>ſheepe; Iohn</hi> 10. gentle in their <hi>inward</hi> quality, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in their <hi>outward</hi> Coate.</p>
            <p>Miſtake not then (my brethren) as <hi>Samuel</hi> did <hi>Gods</hi> call for <hi>Elies:</hi> this <hi>pleaſing</hi> and peaceable gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, is a vertue not only in <hi>Ariſtotles Morall,</hi> but in Gods <hi>Theologicall</hi> Philoſophy: not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7542:11"/>of a <hi>Courtier,</hi> but an ornament of a <hi>true Iſraelite.</hi> Said I an <hi>ornament?</hi> I wronged it, it is the ſoft <hi>wooll</hi> of Chriſts ſheepe, the very <hi>liverie</hi> of Gods Elect, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Put on as the Elect of God bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of mercie, kindneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thinke then on this, I beſeech you (deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) you that <hi>pleaſe</hi> your ſelves too much in the <hi>neglect</hi> of pleaſing others, and in a good (if mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate) oppoſition to flattery, and time ſerving, run too much on the other hand, while you entertaine a <hi>Cynicall</hi> roughneſſe, or ſelfe-conceited <hi>Stiffeneſſe,</hi> too forward to <hi>give offence,</hi> and breake Chriſts peace. If our Lord ſhould come to <hi>feele</hi> out his ſheepe by the <hi>wooll,</hi> to examine your <hi>faith</hi> by your <hi>carriage,</hi> how may you expect to paſſe for <hi>ſheepe,</hi> if with the <hi>Hedge-hogge</hi> yee be all prickles to offend any hand that ſhall <hi>touch</hi> you, yea with the <hi>Porcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine</hi> yee dart quils of <hi>cenſure</hi> at thoſe which <hi>touch you not.</hi> Come about then I pray, and be Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Schollers: that his teaching may <hi>metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſe</hi> you into ſheepe; <hi>teaching</hi> by <hi>precept, Rom.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Let every man pleaſe his neighbour:</hi> and here teaching the ſame by <hi>example, even as I pleaſe.</hi> And <hi>Who is my Neighbour?</hi> is the Lawyers next <hi>quaere: Luke</hi> 10.29. <hi>quibus:</hi> whom muſt we pleaſe? is the next circumſtantiall queſtion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>All men.</hi>] that is, as ſome would have it, <hi>all good men:</hi> and ſo make the <hi>Iew,</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentile</hi> to meet in the <hi>Church of God, Verſe preced.</hi> But it may plainly appeare to bee a large <hi>circumference</hi> drawne about that <hi>triangle,</hi> the <hi>Iew,</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of God, ſtanding in triangular oppoſition each to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7542:12"/>other, and each both to the third: the <hi>Iew</hi> that was under the Law, the <hi>Church</hi> that was under faith, and the <hi>Gentile,</hi> neither under the Law, nor under faith. As hee offended not the fiſh alreadie <hi>within</hi> the net, leſt they ſhould <hi>run out,</hi> ſo hee pleaſed the fiſh <hi>without</hi> the net, that they might <hi>come in:</hi> that they which <hi>obey not the word, may without the word be wonne by conuer ſation.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. As he was 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>iealous</hi> ouer theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> whom he had alreadie <hi>eſpouſed</hi> to Chriſt; ſo was hee <hi>zealous</hi> in wooing more; travailing farre with <hi>Eliezer</hi> to win <hi>Rebecca,</hi> (though a Pagan) <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.22. with <hi>brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Earings,</hi> pleaſing things, ſo to bring her home to his Maſter.</p>
            <p>The Schooles teach us that the ground of true love is the <hi>participation of eternall bleſſedneſſe:</hi> now the prophaneſt worldling, the Turke, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan have in them a <hi>nature capable</hi> of that commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and fellowſhip. There is a <hi>potentia remota,</hi> though not <hi>proxima:</hi> no ſenſible <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> yet no flat <hi>impoſsibilitie,</hi> but that he may one day (for ought I know) be brought to be <hi>partaker of the inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi> Since then there is in me a <hi>deſire,</hi> and in him a <hi>poſsibilitie</hi> (though as yet not no <hi>probabilitie</hi>) that hee may be in good time my <hi>fellow heire of Heaven, and Citizen with the Saints,</hi> I muſt <hi>love</hi> his nature, and wiſh to meet him both in grace and glory, though I <hi>hate</hi> his wickedneſſe <hi>with a perfect hatred,</hi> as the <hi>barre</hi> that yet keepes him out from that communion of bliſſe. And indeed how can I love his <hi>good</hi> if I hate not his <hi>evil?</hi> how can parents love their childrens <hi>ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7542:12"/>and not deteſt their <hi>vices,</hi> that would hurrie them to <hi>damnation? perdita volunt vitia, ſervatos filios;</hi> their deſire is to have their <hi>ſinnes</hi> deſtroyed, and their <hi>ſonnes</hi> ſaved.</p>
            <p>The <hi>perſon</hi> may not be hated for his <hi>faults,</hi> nor the <hi>faults</hi> loved for <hi>the perſon:</hi> the man I muſt <hi>pleaſe,</hi> that I may <hi>ſave</hi> him; his <hi>ſinnes</hi> I muſt let flie at, that I may <hi>kill</hi> them, that elſe would kill <hi>him.</hi> Heedily therefore muſt we aime our arrowes, that we wound not the <hi>perſon</hi> in ſhooting at the <hi>ſinne,</hi> but levell diſcreetly with <hi>Alcons</hi> wary hand, who when hee ſaw a <hi>Dragon</hi> ſeize on, and claſpe about his ſonne, <hi>ſhot</hi> the <hi>Dragon,</hi> and <hi>ſaved</hi> the childe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I cannot but pittie divers good ſoules, whoſe <hi>zeale</hi> in <hi>Iehues</hi> march out-runnes their <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> &amp; with <hi>unadviſed</hi> haſte daſheth them againſt <hi>Salomons</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 7.16.</note> 
               <hi>Iuſtus nimis,</hi> wrapping the <hi>vice</hi> and the <hi>man</hi> in the ſame extremity of <hi>violent</hi> deteſtation. What? <hi>pleaſe</hi> a lewde and prophane man? an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to God and all goodneſſe? no, I <hi>defie</hi> him, as I doe the Deuill and all his workes. Spare a little; there is great difference betweene the <hi>Devill,</hi> and a <hi>deuilliſh</hi> man: the one an enemy <hi>irreconciliable,</hi> the other an enemy, but <hi>may turne</hi> friend. Is he a <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer,</hi> and a <hi>Perſecutor?</hi> ſuch was our Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Is he an <hi>Idolater, Adulterer, &amp;c? And ſuch were ſome of you.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. Secondly, the one is <hi>paſt</hi> redemption, his damnation is <hi>knowne;</hi> So is <hi>not</hi> the other. Thirdly, the Devill I may not <hi>pray</hi> for: for the ſpitefull contemners of Religion I <hi>may,</hi> I <hi>muſt,</hi> even as <hi>Steven, Acts</hi> 7.60. even as <hi>Chriſt, Luke</hi> 23.34. and to looke no further then this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7542:13"/>S. <hi>Paul</hi> forbids <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with Devils, <hi>Verſe</hi> 20. but alloweth fellowſhip with <hi>unbelcevers, Verſe</hi> 27. and Chriſt himſelfe practiſed it, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.2. <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking with Publicans and Sinners,</hi> and none but <hi>Seribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes</hi> cenſured him for it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe hee <hi>that toucheth pitch</hi> may eaſily be <hi>defiled:</hi> nor is it uſuall to find a River like <hi>Hypanis</hi> that keepes the <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> of his water even in the <hi>Salt</hi> Sea: or a righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. that abides unſtained among the impure <hi>Sodomites:</hi> with a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet,</hi> there may follow a <hi>Non expedit,</hi> eſpecially for <hi>weake</hi> ones to have frequent and ordinary <hi>familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> with lewd and ſcandalous people. And though they muſt deſire to <hi>pleaſe</hi> them, by <hi>unoffenſive</hi> carriage, and not to ſhunne them for <hi>contempt,</hi> but only for <hi>caution:</hi> yet it may be for their <hi>ſafetie,</hi> to thinke of diſſolute company, as <hi>Tertullus</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of our <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 24.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, plaguy or <hi>peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fellowes;</hi> whom we ſhould not raſhly frequent without both <hi>ſkill</hi> and <hi>care,</hi> either to doe them ſome <hi>good,</hi> or at leaſt that they doe us no <hi>harme:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we goe neere them fortifie our ſelves with that <hi>Antidote</hi> of <hi>Ieremiahs reſolution, Ier.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Let them turne to thee, doe not thou turne to them:</hi> and all the while weare on thy breaſt before thee that <hi>Amulet</hi> of Saint <hi>Bernard, Vive cantus tibi, utilis alijs, gratus Deo: cautus tibi,</hi> that they may not <hi>pervert</hi> thee, if they <hi>would; utilis alijs,</hi> that thou <hi>convert</hi> them if thou <hi>mayest; gratus Deo,</hi> to become with them, and <hi>pleaſe</hi> them ſo farre, as thou maiſt not <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> God: and how ſarre that is, <hi>Quateniu?</hi> is the laſt <hi>Quaere,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:7542:13"/>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>In all things.</hi>] not only to pleaſe <hi>all</hi> men in <hi>ſome</hi> things; or <hi>ſome</hi> men in <hi>all</hi> things, but the univerſality is <hi>continued,</hi> and <hi>doubled,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>How? <hi>in all things</hi> without exception? Yes, if you underſtand it <hi>adidem;</hi> all <hi>ſuch</hi> things, as come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>omnia licent;</hi> all <hi>lawfull</hi> things. So is <hi>pleaſing</hi> confined, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>for his good to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification:</hi> not for his <hi>evill,</hi> but for his <hi>good:</hi> for his <hi>inſtruction,</hi> not for his <hi>deſtruction.</hi> Saint <hi>Iames</hi> will not owne that for <hi>wiſdome, Iames</hi> 3.17. at leaſt for <hi>heavenly</hi> wiſdome that is not <hi>firſt pure, and then peaceable,</hi> &amp;c. Marke both the <hi>connexion</hi> and <hi>order:</hi> To be <hi>pure</hi> and not <hi>peaceable,</hi> were to attire that Devill <hi>Contention</hi> like an Angell; to be <hi>peaceable</hi> and not <hi>pure,</hi> were to cloath that Angell <hi>Peace</hi> like a Devill: To be <hi>firſt</hi> peaceable and <hi>then</hi> pure, were to ſalute the <hi>ſervant</hi> before the <hi>Maſter,</hi> and preferre <hi>men</hi> before <hi>God:</hi> but to be <hi>firſt pure</hi> and <hi>then</hi> peaceable is fairely to <hi>aſcend</hi> up to God in a good <hi>conſcience,</hi> and orderly to <hi>deſcend</hi> downe to men in good <hi>correſpondence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>generalia decipiunt:</hi> therefore come wee more particularly to view the bound-ſtone, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>All things:</hi> and in our way conſider that <hi>All things</hi> in generall, under which our <hi>all things</hi> in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall are contained, are of three ſorts: <hi>bona, mala, media,</hi> the <hi>good</hi> like the tree of <hi>life</hi> hath <hi>Oportet</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven, his ſound is invitation, <hi>Guſtate &amp; videte:</hi> his fruit is peace, <hi>Ecce quam bonum &amp; quam iucundum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>evill</hi> like the <hi>for bidden</hi> tree, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.3. <hi>in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio paradiſi,</hi> next to hand, hath <hi>non licet</hi> written, his ſound is prohibition; <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> his fruit
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7542:14"/>deſtruction <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The middle are things <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> in their nature and <hi>eſſence</hi> neither <hi>good</hi> nor <hi>bad,</hi> but in their act and <hi>existence</hi> no longer neutrals, but either good in their <hi>uſe,</hi> or ill in their <hi>abuſe:</hi> good when we <hi>pleaſe,</hi> evill when we <hi>give offence</hi> by them. The <hi>evill</hi> is forbidden, the <hi>good</hi> commanded, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> neither forbidden nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>evill;</hi> wee may not <hi>pleaſe</hi> any man in <hi>ſinne:</hi> we may not <hi>ſinne</hi> to <hi>pleaſe</hi> any man. Will you have the <hi>Embleme</hi> of a Flatterer? take the little <hi>Wren</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trochilus.</note> who to <hi>feed his owne belly</hi> picketh the <hi>Crocodiles</hi> teeth, and with his tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and <hi>pleaſing</hi> delight cauſeth him to yawne wide: which <hi>Ichneumon,</hi> the Rat of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and taking that advantage, ſhooteth ſuddenly into the bowels of the Crocodile, and eateth ont his belly. They that <hi>pleaſe</hi> for advantage, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour men ſecurely <hi>ſleeping</hi> in their ſinnes, performe ſuch another office, in making open way for the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> of <hi>Eden.</hi> I remember that once the <hi>Devill</hi> taught that beaſt to <hi>ſpeake, Gen.</hi> 3. and it was to <hi>pleaſe</hi> his Maſter, thereby to tickle him to <hi>death: yee ſhall be as Gods:</hi> And once I finde <hi>God</hi> opened the mouth of a beaſt, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.28. and hee ſpake to <hi>reprove</hi> his offending Maſter, and to <hi>ſave</hi> him by <hi>diſpleaſing</hi> him. I leave you to iudge whether the plaine tell-troth <hi>Aſſe</hi> were not a better ſervant, then the ſubtile flattering <hi>Serpent.</hi> For if I ſhould <hi>pleaſe</hi> any man by heartning and hardning him in ſinne, I <hi>rivet</hi> it faſter upon him, and yet I ſhould make the ſinne <hi>mine</hi> owne; a poore piece of friendſhip, if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7542:14"/>inſteed of <hi>ſaving</hi> my friend from drowning, I ſhould lovingly <hi>embrace</hi> him, and keepe <hi>him</hi> under water, and my <hi>ſelfe</hi> with him.</p>
            <p>As I may not <hi>pleaſe</hi> him in <hi>ſinne,</hi> ſo neither may I <hi>ſinne</hi> to <hi>pleaſe</hi> him; not by <hi>ſocietie</hi> in ſinne, leaſt <hi>running into the ſame exceſſe of riot</hi> (1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4.) if I light in bad company, I ſhould goe to Hell with them for <hi>good-fellowſhip;</hi> if the <hi>fellowſhip</hi> in going to <hi>Hell</hi> may be called <hi>good.</hi> Vnhappy <hi>knots</hi> of Satans tying, who coupleth men as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the foxes, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 15.4. with a <hi>firebrand</hi> betweene them to burne <hi>themſelves</hi> and our <hi>corne.</hi> I ſay, our corne. For if the ſearch ſhould goe now as then, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Quis hoc fecit?</hi> Who hath brought this dearth of Corne, Mault, &amp;c? I beleeve the <hi>hue and crie</hi> would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the <hi>drunken</hi> Epicure upon ſtrong ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, that hee forceth God, to <hi>pull the cup from his mouth,</hi> becauſe being <hi>filled</hi> with Gods plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, hee <hi>vomited</hi> his bounty into the Donors bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
            <p>Yea more, I may not <hi>ſinne</hi> to pleaſe, though in the <hi>pleaſing</hi> I might <hi>profit:</hi> as it muſt be, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.2. ſo it muſt be only <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in</hi> good, as well as <hi>for</hi> good. I may not ſinne to preſerve <hi>peace,</hi> then which nothing more lovely, no nor to ſave a <hi>life,</hi> then which nothing more ſweet.</p>
            <p>Yet more, I may not <hi>ſinne</hi> to pleaſe, though for ſome <hi>ſpirituall</hi> good; as to keepe off ſin from ſome other, and draw it on my ſelfe; no not to prevent another ſinne in my ſelfe: in evils of <hi>puniſhment, è malis minimum,</hi> but in evill of <hi>ſinne, è malis nullum.</hi> No nor yet may I doe it for the end of all ends the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7542:15"/>
               <hi>glory</hi> of God; leaſt God take us up, as <hi>Iob</hi> did his friend, <hi>Will yee ſpeake wickedly for God? Iob.</hi> 31.7. <hi>non defenſoribus istis, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One exception, and that out of Scripture will keepe <hi>All things</hi> within his bankes. A Chriſtian may <hi>pleaſe</hi> and condeſcend, in all things, as Chriſt did condeſcend, and <hi>was tempted like us in all things, (Heb.</hi> 4.15.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſinne only excepted.</hi> Here then is the difference betweene the <hi>fawning</hi> flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and the <hi>pleaſing Chriſtian:</hi> the flatterer that feeds on the aire of mens favour like the <hi>Cameleon,</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of the next obiect, any colour ſave <hi>white,</hi> the Hieroglipheke of <hi>innocence:</hi> but the good Chriſtian, whoſe meate is more ſolide, <hi>profiting</hi> and <hi>ſaving,</hi> will ſuite to any colour ſave <hi>blacke,</hi> the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in <hi>Good</hi> things we muſt <hi>pleaſe,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ioyning the <hi>adverbe</hi> with the <hi>nowne,</hi> in doing a <hi>good</hi> thing <hi>well,</hi> in a good and unoffenſive man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but alſo, ſometimes in <hi>for bearing</hi> it, where is danger of <hi>offence.</hi> What? (will you ſay) is not <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioboni mala?</hi> and will you
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3 8.</note> 
               <hi>doe evill that good may come thereof?</hi> yea the omiſſion of <hi>good</hi> is the <hi>evill</hi> of omiſſion; and <hi>ſimply</hi> evill, when the duties are ſimply <hi>neceſſary:</hi> but ſince <hi>affirmative</hi> precepts binde not <hi>adſemper</hi> (it being impoſſible to do them all at once) charity muſt looke out with the eyes of <hi>diſcretion,</hi> for the <hi>ubi</hi> and <hi>quando,</hi> and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances neceſſary attendants on vertuous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. A wiſe man will thinke what the wiſeman ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1. <hi>There is a time for all things.</hi> If thou ſuffer thy brother to ſin, thou ſinneſt in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7542:15"/>
               <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt plainely rebuke him:</hi> and yet I may <hi>ſin</hi> in <hi>reprooving,</hi> if I <hi>reproue</hi> him for ſin <hi>unfeaſonably,</hi> when he is in paſſion, as mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring Phyſicke in the <hi>fitt.</hi> Againe, <hi>We can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt the Trueth, but for the Trueth,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. Yet to avoid offence, <hi>ſometimes ſome</hi> truths may be concealed. For though we need not ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at <hi>ſcandalum Phariſaeorum,</hi> malitious excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but keepe on our way, and turne them off with Chriſt's <hi>Let them alone, &amp;c. Mat.</hi> 15.12, 14. yet wee muſt be ſo tender of <hi>Scandalum Puſillorum,</hi> ſuch as ſtumble of weaknes, as to prevent their offence, our hand may hold from <hi>doing</hi> ſome kinde of <hi>good</hi> not preſently neceſſary, and our tongue from <hi>ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> ſome <hi>truth</hi> not importantly materiall; but <hi>to deferre</hi> the one, and <hi>conceale</hi> the other, untill by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and mature inſtruction that rocke of offence (like the dead body of <hi>Amaſa</hi>) be remoued out of the way. For as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> adviſeth, Whatſoever ſpirituall good may be omitted without preiudice to that triple trueth <hi>of life, of righteouſnes,</hi> and <hi>of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> we ſhould let it paſſe (underſtand <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> that is, <hi>deferre</hi> or <hi>conceale</hi> it) rather then <hi>give offence to Iew or Gentile or the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Indifferent</hi> things, which are our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>All,</hi> and the maine obiect of <hi>pleaſing in all things:</hi> in all things <hi>indifferent,</hi> wherein God hath not tyed up our hands, by any either <hi>expreſſe</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite</hi> command; but left us <hi>in bivio,</hi> upon due weighing of circumſtances to <hi>take</hi> or <hi>leave.</hi> So that as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>In medijs lex poſitaeſt obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae;</hi> ſo in theſe indifferent things <hi>eſpecially</hi> muſt we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7542:16"/>ſhew ourſelves peaceable, inoffenſive, <hi>pleaſing,</hi> that we neither wound <hi>in</hi> them, or <hi>for</hi> them, our weake Brother by <hi>ſcandall,</hi> or authority by <hi>contempt,</hi> or the Church by <hi>faction.</hi> That where <hi>humane</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity commandeth, and <hi>divine</hi> authority doth not countermaund, we retaine our <hi>conſcience</hi> free from <hi>Doctrinall</hi> neceſſity, yet ſtooping the <hi>outward</hi> Man to <hi>Obedientiall</hi> neceſſity, <hi>Yee muſt needes be ſubiect. Rom.</hi> 13.5. and that not patience perforce, <hi>not onely becauſe of wrath, but for conſcience ſake.</hi> For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit ſuch lawes of man lay not any <hi>direct</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate</hi> tye upon the Conſcience <hi>(There is one Lawgiver that can ſave or deſtroy, (Iam.</hi> 4.12.) Yet they ſo bind us <hi>indirectly</hi> and <hi>mediately,</hi> that <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God,</hi> and is bound over upon breach of the good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>they that reſiſt, receive to themſelves damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rom.</hi> 13.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> telleth vs that <hi>Snakes</hi> encompaſſed in a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>Betony, fight</hi> one with another till they kill each other, and will not to the death come over that <hi>incloſure.</hi> If either the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the Realme, or the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the Church, ſhould lay a tie of <hi>ſin</hi> upon us, in ſuch caſe ſhould we ſhew Chriſtian valour, (yet not in <hi>reſiſting</hi> or <hi>ſtriking,</hi> but) <hi>ſuffering</hi> blowes, wounds, martyrdome, rather then vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late that Axiome, <hi>We muſt obey Godrather then men, Act.</hi> 5.29. But while we may obey them not <hi>contra Deum,</hi> but <hi>ſub Deo, in Deo;</hi> yea and obey <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Men</hi> who are the <hi>powers ordained of God,</hi> he expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth we ſhould peaceably and humbly <hi>ſubmit</hi> our ſelves
<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7542:16"/>In a word; where there is no danger of ſin in <hi>keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the peace of the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> it is a ſin to <hi>break</hi> the peace: and every <hi>moderate</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that owneth God for his <hi>Father,</hi> and the Church for his <hi>Mother,</hi> muſt learne for their ſakes to doe as our Apoſtle here exampleth us, <hi>pleaſe all men in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould now have deſcended to particular appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſuitable to this auditory, and the times; and have ſolicited you (my Brethren, who as Trumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are much heard among the multitude) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the part of <hi>Gracchus</hi> his man, who ſtanding behind his Maſter with an Ivory Pipe, when ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe in declayming tranſported him beyond the due compaſſe of his voice, uſed with ſounding a temperate note, to bring him to a lower key, <hi>à nimia contentione revocare:</hi> that by your <hi>moderate</hi> and peaceable <hi>cariage</hi> and <hi>counſell,</hi> ye might qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the offences taken both in Church and State, by unhappy diſtractions and miſpriſions of the time. But I ſpeake to ſuch an Auditory as (though I doe not) your ſelves can ſufficiently apply.</p>
            <p>To you Right Reverend Viſitour, I can make no other application, but humbly to beſeech you to doe as you doe: in the eminent luſtre of your <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> meekenes, follow our Apoſtles example to be example to all your flocke. And might you ever with the <hi>Maſter-Bee,</hi> governe without a ſting, and doe all by the <hi>ſpirit of meekenes</hi> without vſe of the <hi>Rod,</hi> but that you may obſerve ſometimes when the <hi>rod</hi> is out of hand, and <hi>caſt on the ground, it tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to a Serpent, Exod.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:7542:17"/>
            <p>To thoſe that have the ſubordinate exerciſe of iurisdiction &amp; their Miniſters, I make no other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, but deſire they will take the latter part of my text for a comment on their proceſſe: <hi>Ex of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio mero,</hi> that is, <hi>Not ſeeking-mine owne profit, Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem corum concernent',</hi> that is, <hi>ſeeking the profit of many that they may be ſaved.</hi> Let the <hi>proceeding</hi> be according to your <hi>proceſſe,</hi> and my Text; and yee muzzle the mouthes of all contradiction.</p>
            <p>The Church-wardens and Sidemen, I briefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to remember, that they may not <hi>pleaſe</hi> their <hi>neighbours</hi> in their <hi>ſin,</hi> nor <hi>ſin</hi> to pleaſe their <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> Bring forth conſcionably their faults to the Court of <hi>Reformation,</hi> and <hi>ſeeke the profit</hi> of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, that <hi>they may be ſaved:</hi> at leaſt, be carefull <hi>to deliver your owne ſoules, Ezek.</hi> 3.19. and not for any mans pleaſure to wrap your ſelves in the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſin of periury.</p>
            <p>And now that I have ended <hi>my</hi> worke, beſeech we the Lord to begin <hi>his;</hi> and to give us grace, ſo conſcionably and Chriſtianly to <hi>pleaſe all men in all things,</hi> that wee may pleaſe him <hi>above</hi> all, and in ſervice of the Prince of peace, <hi>endeavouring to keepe the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace,</hi> we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that peace of God, <hi>that paſſeth all underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding:</hi> which keepe our hearts and minds, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7542:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
